<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.2"
         xml:id="cha-yast-serviceman">
   <title>Service management with YaST</title>
   <info>
      <abstract>
         <para>YaST provides a service manager for controlling the default system target, services, displaying service status, and reading the log file. New in <phrase role="productname">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</phrase><phrase role="productnumber">15 SP7</phrase> is YaST support for <systemitem class="daemon">systemd</systemitem> socket-based services activation, which configures services to start on demand.</para>
      </abstract>
   </info>
   <para><systemitem class="daemon">systemd</systemitem> supports starting services with socket-based activation, for starting services on demand. These services have two unit types: service and socket. For example, CUPS is controlled by <filename>cups.service</filename> and <filename>cups.socket</filename>. YaST allows you to select the type of service start-up you want to use.</para>
   <para><xref linkend="fig-yast-serviceman"/> shows the options in the Start Mode drop-down box: <guimenu>On Boot</guimenu>, <guimenu>On Demand</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Manually</guimenu>. Select <guimenu>On Demand</guimenu> for socket-based activation. This opens a listening network socket, and the service starts when there is a request.</para>
   <figure xml:id="fig-yast-serviceman">
      <title>YaST service manager</title>
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject outputformat="print">
            <imagedata fileref="media/yast2_servicemanager.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject outputformat="screen">
            <imagedata fileref="media/yast2_servicemanager.png" width="100%"/>
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>The <guimenu>On Demand</guimenu> option is visible only for services that support it. Currently this is a small subset of services, such as CUPS, dbus, iscsid, iscsiuio, multipathd, pcscd, rpcbind, TFTP, virtlockd, virtlogd. See <command>man 5 systemd.socket</command> for detailed information on how socket activation works.</para>
</chapter>
